Register of the Vladimir Konstantinovich Bukovskiĭ papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1979-1981
  - Nuclear Forces Treaty (INF Treaty) between the United States of America and the Soviet Union, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 35: 6-7)
    Includes statements, correspondence, and clippings.
  - Nuclear Free Zone campaign, 1984 (Box-folder 36: 8)
    Newsletter and clippings.
  - Political abuse of psychiatry in the Soviet Union, 1976-1994 (Box-folder 36: 9-10)
    Includes Lateral'naia terapiia, rukovodstvo dlia vrachei, by A. P., Chuprikov, A. N. Linev, and I. A. Martsenkovskii, Kiev, 1994.
  - Promotion of democracy in communist countries, 1984 (Box-folder 36: 11)
    Includes a program, reports, and printed matter.
  - Religious freedom in the Soviet Union, 1986 (Box-folder 36: 12)
  - Right to conscientious objection, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 36: 13)
    Includes appeals, clippings, and other materials relating to the fate of the draft resister Olivier Du Puis.
  - Soviet-American relations, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 36: 14)
    Clippings and notes.
  - Soviet dissident movement, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 35: 1-4)
    Includes correspondence, clippings, newsletters, and other printed matter.
  - Soviet economic performance and forecasts, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 35: 5-6)
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and clippings.
  - Soviet influence on the peace movement, 1981-1985
    Includes correspondence, clippings, and printed matter.
    - Vladimir Bukovskiĭ's personal involvement in the peace movement, 1981-1985
      - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 35: 7)
      - Writings, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 35: 8)
      - Clippings, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 35: 9)
    - Arguments against peace movement, 1981 (Box-folder 35: 10)
    - Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament (CND) and other groups, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 35: 11-12)
      Correspondence, reports, brochures, pamphlets, and clippings.
    - World Peace Council and communist penetration, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 37: 1-2)
      Correspondence, reports, and clippings
  - Soviet Jewry emigration rights, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 37: 3-5)
    Includes correspondence, appeals, and clippings.
  - United States-Soviet Union trade relations, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 37: 6-9)
    Includes "Remarks by Senator Robert J. Dole at the Second Session of the 1986 Forum on U.S.-Soviet Trade Relations," typescript, April 24, 1985.
  - United States broadcasting to the Soviet Union, 1978-1991
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 38: 1-2)
    - Memoranda, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 38: 3)
    - Program reviews, 1986 (Box-folder 38: 4)
    - Reports, 1984 (Box-folder 38: 5)
      Includes The Board for International Broadcasting: 1984 Annual Report.
    - Research materials, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 38: 6-8)
      Articles, clippings, and brochures.
    - Soviet Media Daily Digest, Radio Liberty, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 38: 9)
  - World Disarmament campaign, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 38: 10)
- Speeches and Writings by Others, 1965-2000
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - General, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 38: 11)
  - Aksenov, Vasilii, "The Inspector General Goes to Topeka," typescript, circa 1984 (Box-folder 38: 12)
  - Alburt, Lev and Larry Parr, "Will Gorbachev, Like Lenin, Always Be With Us?," typescript, circa 1985 (Box-folder 38: 13)
  - Aleinikov, Vladimir, Puteshestviia pamiati Rembo, and other poems, 1965-1990 (Box-folder 38: 14, Box-folder 39: 1)
  - Chalfont, Alan, The Great Unilateralist Illusion, 1983 (Box-folder 39: 2)
  - Clay, Jason W. and Bonnie K. Holcomb, Politics and the Ethiopian Famine 1984-1985 (Box-folder 39: 3)
  - Epstein, Edward Jay, 133 Questions, 1990 (Box-folder 39: 4)
  - Gubar', Iurii, poems, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 39: 5)
  - Hatch, Orrin, articles, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 39: 6)
  - Holzer, Erika, U. S. Peace Movement Rooted in Fear and Guilt, Soviet Dissident Says, 1986 (Box-folder 39: 7)
  - Isakova, Elena, "Veter v kandalakh," typescript, circa 1991 (Box-folder 39: 8)
  - Joshua, Wynfred, Soviet Manipulation of the European Peace Movement, 1983 (Box-folder 39: 9)
  - Kennan, George F., Containment of Communism, 1984 (Box-folder 39: 10)
  - Keyes, Gene, "Vladimir Bukovskii and the Fear-Fighters: Nonviolent Protest Demonstrations in the Soviet Union 1961-1972, a Chronology of Events, an Annotated Bibliography," typescript, 1991 (Box-folder 39: 11)
  - Kropivnitskii, Evgenii, Zemnoi uiut, 1990 (Box-folder 39: 12)
  - Kublanovskii, Iurii, Ottisk, 1990 (Box-folder 39: 13)
  - Litvinenko, Aleksandr, and Iurii Fel'shtinskii, "FSB vzryvaet Rosiiu," typescript, circa 2000 (Box-folder 39: 14)
  - O'Hallaron, Carol, "Hard Bargainer on Human Rights Vladimir Bukovsky on Helsinki Accords," typescript, circa 1980 (Box-folder 39: 15)
  - Pipes, Richard, Can the Soviet Union Change, circa 1985 (Box-folder 39: 16)
  - Pilon, Juliana Geran, Soviet Active Measures - The Philosophical Background, 1985 (Box-folder 39: 17)
  - Rogatshi (Rogachii), Inna, Oletko suorittanut ihmisoikeus- tutkinnon?, 1989 (Box-folder 39: 18)
  - Rowen, Henry, "Gorbachev Probably Will Be Seeking Relief and Help From the West," typescript, 1985 (Box-folder 40: 1)
  - Rozek, Edward J., Henry Kissinger: The Switch-Doctor, 1982 (Box-folder 40: 2)
  - Sapgir, Genrikh, Sonety na rubashkakh, 1989 (Box-folder 40: 3)
  - Shtromas, Alexander, 1981, 1985
    - Political Change and Social Development: The Case of the Soviet Union, 1981 (Box-folder 40: 4)
    - How the End of the Soviet System May Come About: Historical Precedents and Possible Scenarios, 1985 (Box-folder 40: 5)
  - Singer, Max, Dynamic Containment, circa 1980 (Box-folder 40: 6)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Alexander, A World Split Apart - Commencement Address Delivered At Harvard University, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 40: 7)
    Includes other articles.
  - Thatcher, Margaret, "Speech at the Mendeleev Institute," Moscow, Russia, typescript, 1993 (Box-folder 40: 8)
  - Wolzak, Robert van Voren en Henk, Vredesactivisten Tegen de Verde door Vladimir Boekovski, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 40: 9)
    Includes other articles by Wolzak.
  - Zahaykevich, Marta, "The Hermeneutics of Dissent: Philosophical Worldviews and the Interpretations on Political Repression of Soviet Human Rights Activists," typescript, 1982 (Box-folder 40: 10)
- Personal Files, 1983-2000
  - General, circa 1990 (Box-folder 40: 11)
    Includes submitted applications and curriculum vitae for jobs.
  - Vladimir Natanovich Fleishgakker's court case file, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 40: 12)
  - Viktor Makarov file, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 40: 13)
  - Aleksei Tumerman's court case file, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 40: 14-15)
    Includes Bukovskiĭ’s letter in support of A. Tumerman’s application for bail pending appeal.
- Printed Matter, 1928-2010
  - General, 1979-1986 (Box-folder 40: 16, Box-folder 55: 24)
    Includes pamphlets, leaflets, and posters.
  - Commentary, Volume 86, No. 5, 1988 (Box-folder 40: 17)
  - Democracy Bulletin, Vol. 1, Nos. 1-2, 1983 (Box-folder 40: 18)
  - Foreign Affairs Note, United States Department of State, Washington, D.C., 1981-1982 (Box-folder 40: 19)
  - Freedom at Issue, Nos. 68-69, 1982 (Box-folder 41: 1)
  - Konstitutsiia (osnovnoi zakon) Soiuza Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik, 1975 (Box-folder 41: 2)
  - Joan C. Baez, programme booklet, circa 1980 (Box-folder 54: 28)
  - No Substitute for Peace, report by the Centre for Conflict Studies, University of New Brunswick, Canada, 1982 (Box-folder 41: 3)
  - Postcards by Mikhail Shemiakin, circa 1990 (Box-folder 55: 23)
  - Pacifisme, Neutralisme Et Dangers De Guerre, Dossier de presse, Institut D'Histoire Sociale, Paris, 1981 (Box-folder 41: 4)
  - Russian parliamentary and presidential elections, 1991-2010 (Box-folder 41: 5-13, Box-folder 42: 1-4)
    Includes pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, business cards, and other printed matter.
  - Sovetskoe foto: vystavka sovetskoi fotografii za 10 let, 1928 (Box-folder 42: 5)
  - Vardo Bulletin, No. 2, Stockholm, 1991 (Box-folder 42: 6)
  - USSR Today: Viewed in Radio Liberty Monitoring, Nos. 89-104, 106, 108, 111, 1986 (Box-folder 42: 7-11)
- Bukovskiĭ Testimony Project File, 1937-1995
  Photocopies of classified documents of the Politburo and the Secretariat of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union. Includes correspondence, statements, and other related materials.
  - Correspondence, 1991-1995
    - General, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 43: 1)
    - Anastasi, Paul (Free Press), 1992-1995 (Box-folder 43: 2)
    - Birman, Igor', 1992 (Box-folder 43: 3)
    - Borovoi, V., 1993 (Box-folder 43: 4)
    - Brian Lapping Associate, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 5)
    - The Britain-Russia Centre, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 6)
    - Burbulis, Gennadii, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 7)
    - DeMuth, Christopher (American Enterprise Institute), 1992 (Box-folder 43: 8)
    - Fujita, Yukihisa, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 9)
    - Geneva Initiative, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 10)
    - Golgsmith, James, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 43: 11)
    - Gordievskii, Oleg, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 12)
    - Lupan, Viktor, 1993 (Box-folder 43: 13)
    - Moskovskie novosti, 1993 (Box-folder 43: 14)
    - Pikhoia, R. G., 1992 (Box-folder 43: 15)
    - Podhoretz, Norman, 1994 (Box-folder 43: 16)
    - Raisian, John, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 17)
    - Rogachii (Rogatshi), Inna, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 43: 18)
    - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr Isaevich, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 19)
    - Staffa, Dario, 1994 (Box-folder 43: 20)
    - Thatcher, Margaret, 1992 (Box-folder 43: 21)
  - Organizational documents, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 43: 22)
    Includes statements to the press by Bukovskiĭ and other materials relating to the testimonial project.
  - Photocopies of archival documents, 1937-1994
    - 1937 (Box-folder 43: 23)
    - 1938 (Box-folder 43: 24)
    - 1953 (Box-folder 43: 25)
    - 1956 (Box-folder 43: 26)
    - 1957 (Box-folder 43: 27)
    - 1958 (Box-folder 44: 1)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 44: 2)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 44: 3)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 44: 4)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 44: 5)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 44: 6)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 44: 7)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 44: 8)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 44: 9)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 44: 10)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 44: 11)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 44: 12)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 44: 13)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 44: 14)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 45: 1)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 45: 2-3)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 45: 4-5)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 45: 6-10)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 46: 1-2)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 46: 3-5)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 46: 6-10, Box-folder 47: 1)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 48: 1-8, Box-folder 47: 2-8)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 48: 9-10, Box-folder 49: 1-3)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 49: 4)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 49: 5)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 49: 6)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 49: 7)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 49: 8)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 49: 9)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 49: 10)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 49: 11)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 50: 1)
    - 1991 (Box-folder 50: 2)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 50: 3)
    - 1994 (Box-folder 50: 4)
- Oversize Material, 1976-1988
  - Awards and honorary degrees, 1979-1988
    - "70 Let Ceskoslovenske Republiky," CSL Obeg Legionarska, medal, 1988 (Box 57)
    - "Friends of Freedom," The Coalition for a Democratic Majority, certificate and medal, 1979 (Box-folder 56: 1, Box 57)
    - "Honorary Fellow," del Meeting per L'Amiciza Fra i Popoli a Rimini, certificate, 1981 (Box-folder 56: 1)
    - "Let Your Light Shine," University of Colorado, Boulder, medal, circa 1980 (Box 57)
    - "Roger Salengro," Maire de Lille, medal, circa 1980 (Box 57)
    - "Shelby Cullom Davis Award," Ethics and Public Policy Center, 1987 (Box-folder 56: 1)
  - Bukovskiĭ's debates advertising posters, 1980 (Box-folder 56: 2)
  - Graphic art by A. Muravnich, 1976 (Box-folder 56: 3)
- Sound Recording, undated (Box-folder 54: 29)
  Includes one compact sound cassette: "Rosemary Troughton and Dr. Kronid Liubarskii."
- Electronic Records, undated (Box-folder 55: 27)
  8 3.5" discs, untitled, undated.